Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim,
and this is Geshe Michael Roach.
We're ready now to start the actual
back into the Lam Rim text.
What's exciting is that we have reached
NYIN BCU BDUN PAR
It means, this is an
announcement in the text,
that we have reached the
17th day of teaching.
So, don't forget that this entire book
was a twenty four day teaching
by the great Pabongka Rinpoche,
who was also a teacher
of my teacher's teacher,
and one of the greatest books
ever written in Tibetan,
maybe the greatest.
NYIN BCU BDUN PAR means
we're starting on the record
of the 17th day of teachings.
That makes us about 80% finished.
We started this book I
guess over 10 years ago,
and personally I'm just enjoying the book.
I'm not trying to get through it
and try to finish it by certain date.
I'm not thinking like that.
I'm trying to, personally,
I'm trying to enjoy it
and go through it very...
with a lot of pleasure and enjoyment.
I don't know, maybe like
people drink a fine wine.
I don't know, but just,
you don't rush to finish the bottle.
You just sit and enjoy it.
So we're enjoying the Lam Rim together.
And, personally, I don't
care how long it takes.
I think we should do it very deeply.
In this course, we are
going to do it deeply.
So we're about 80% finished.
There's twenty four days
total. But don't forget,
we finished two of those
days already towards the end.
And that's the teaching on
meditation and wisdom, emptiness.
We did those at the
beginning of this 10 years
because we wanted to use the meditations
during the Lam Rim classes.
So we've actually finished
about 80% of the text.
I guess we can finish in
about four or five more years.
Then I made you a promise for dessert.
We're going to go to the great,
greatest Lam Rim emptiness
teaching of ever.
The emptiness teaching in this Lam Rim,
called the Gift of Liberation
Thrust into the Palm of Your Hand.
The presentation of emptiness
is actually not that long.
The reason is that
Tsongkapa did it so well
and so long with Manjushri's help.
I think Pabongka Rinpoche was thinking,
Oh, we don't have to,
we don't have to cover it that much here.
So we're going to go, after
we finished this Lam Rim,
we're going to go study
the emptiness chapter
in the meditation chapter
from Tsongkapa's great book
on the Steps of the Path,
which is LAM RIM CHEN MO
That will take us about
six years, so don't worry.
We have only about ten years left to go.
Don't gobble down this fine wine.
Enjoy it. Have fun.
It's a way of life.
Lam Rim is not a book.
Lam Rim is a way of life
for the rest of your life.
If you can get Lam Rim teachings
for most of your adult life, which I did,
you'll be very grateful.
It keeps your life going straight,
through all the changes
that we have in our life.
The Lam Rim can be the one steady thing
that you keep doing
through your whole life.
Here we go.
NYIN BCU BDUN PAR
RGYAL SRAS CHEN PO ZHI BA LHA'I ZHAL NAS
means let's talk, I'd like
to give you a quotation
from that great bodhisattva
RGYAL SRAS CHEN PO ZHI BA LHA
Shantideva
Here's the quotation:
,GANG LA SEMS KYI DAM PA RIN CHEN DE,
,SKYES PA DE YI SKU LA PHYAG 'TSAL ZHING,
,GANG LA GNOD PA BYAS KYANG BDE 'BREL BA,
,BDE BA'I 'BYUNG GNAS
DE LA SKYABS SU MCHI,
I bow down
to that precious state of mind,
to the jewel of that state of mind.
Well what state of mind are
you talking about Shantideva?
He says, Well, there's a state of mind
that if you have it and
someone bows down to you,
they make incredible good karma.
We talked about it in the coffee shop.
If you're a secret
bodhisattva, which you can be,
and you're sitting in the coffee shop,
and somebody offers you a coffee,
they get like a billion
years of good karma.
It's so cool.
It's so sexy to be the
person who can quietly
make other people a billion
years of good karma,
just by buying a coffee from them.
But obviously, if they
make a prostration to you,
they will get intense good karma.
Now comes controversial part.
GANG LA GNOD PA BYAS KYANG BDE 'BREL BA
Wouldn't it be cool to
be the kind of person
that if someone hurt you,
they would make good karma?
What?
If someone hurt you, they
would make good karma.
Come on, Geshe-la, we know many examples.
If you do bad thing to bodhisattva,
you get bad karma for a long, long time.
Yes. But something happens cool.
Even if you hurt a bodhisattva,
you get BDE 'BREL
BDE 'BREL means
you make a karmic connection
with them, you see.
Even if you yell at a bodhisattva
or you say something bad
about this bodhisattva,
then, of course you make a bad seed.
But you also make a connection
seed with the bodhisattva.
It's very interesting.
That will bring you happiness
for millions of lifetimes.
It's so cool.
So if I can become bodhisattva,
if I can have bodhisattva's vision,
then of course, if someone
serves me a coffee,
secretly, I will give them a
billion years of good karma.
That's sweet.
Oh and even if they yell at
me or they call me stupid,
"Geshe Michael, you're stupid."
Then of course, they
will make some bad karma
but they will make this
karma of connection
with a bodhisattva.
And that karma is much more powerful.
They will have this very
sweet karma of connection
with the bodhisattva.
So Shantideva is bowing
down to bodhichitta
because of it's beautiful qualities.
It's like a jewel.
It's like a wish-giving jewel.
GANG ZHIG RGYUD LA SKYES PA DE LA
SKUR BA 'DEBS PA SOGS NGAN PA'I
'BREL BA BZHAG PA TSUN KYANG
Even if you do the worst thing possible
to bodhisattva, and you
criticize them. and spit on them,
or you something, you say
bad things about them.
TSUN KYANG even up to,
GTAN GYI BDE BAR 'GOD PAR
MDZAD PA'I PHAN YON CAN
That bodhichitta can
still give you Buddhahood.
Even from making a bad
connection with a bodhisattva,
because you made a connection
with a bodhisattva,
that bodhichitta is so powerful
that somehow it's going
to take those other people
to enlightenment when they criticize you.
So that's kind of cool, right?
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS KYI PHAN
YON 'GA' ZHIG GSUNGS NAS
This GSUNGS NAS means - our Lama
started out the seventeenth day
by reminding us of how
cool is bodhichitta.
GSUNGS means he reminded us.
PHAN YON 'GA' ZHIG means
he threw in a couple
of more benefits about bodhichitta
that he did not mention
in the previous day.
He added some more.
That what's the new benefit we have?
Insult a bodhisattva
and you make a connection
to become a Buddha.
Yay!
MDOR NA SEMS 'DIS ZIN
PA'I BYAS TSAD CHOS DANG
There's a very important
word here called ZIN PA
Z-I-N-P-A.
ZIN PA
Very, very important word.
It's very difficult to
translate into English
but it means, I don't know,
when you're in high school
and your hormones are flowing strong,
which in some men don't
finish until you're 85 or 90.
I don't know.
But you fall in love
with every girl you see
on the street.
We were talking about Don Juan, right?
No, Don Quixote.
Sorry.
That he fall in love with this bar girl.
What's her name?
I forgot.
I forgot her name.
Anyway, if the young man fall in love
with this girl in high school,
then all the time he's thinking
about her, all the time.
He's driving, he's thinking about...
Everything reminds him
of this new girl he met in the high school
and that's called ZIN PA
In Tibetan that's called ZIN PA
His mind is captured by
these feelings for the girl.
In the bodhisattva's mind,
ZIN PA captured by this
feeling that I would like
to become a Buddha for everybody.
ZIN PA
That's ZIN PA
MDOR NA SEMS 'DIS ZIN PA'I BYAS TSAD CHOS
means once you have
bodhichitta stuck in your mind,
like that cute girl's
picture in your mind,
from that time,
DE'ANG SANGS RGYAS KYI
RGYU THEG CHEN GYI CHOS
SU 'GRO BA YIN PA'I PHYIR
Then anything you do becomes a cause
for your enlightenment.
Once you are thinking about this girl,
meaning this Buddhahood,
then it doesn't matter what you do.
That becomes a cause for Buddhahood.
And we have a picture here,
it's a guy taking a walk with his dog
or a lady taking a walk
with her husband and a dog.
Just if a bodhisattva
has got the bodhisattva
state of mind in their mind,
bodhisattva vision of
dancing between planets,
if they have that in their mind,
then everything they do is dharma.
That's really cool.
Like you don't have to go to the temple
and read a Medicine Buddha Sutra.
Go for a walk with your
dog and your husband,
that's dharma.
If you're thinking about
this vision that I would like
to dance between many
planets and help people.
If you're thinking about that,
then everything you do,
you brush your teeth,
I don't know,
you watch Netflix,
everything you do becomes dharma.
It's very beautiful.
It's very, very cool.
Let's go to the next sentence.
SGRUB PA NYAMS LEN BYED PA LA
Now he says
let's put it in the context of practice.
SGRUB PA NYAMS LEN means
how does this bodhisattva's vision
going to affect your Buddhist practice?
LHA BGSOM SNGAGS BZLAS TZAM
LAS BYED RGYU MED PA BZHIN
MI BYED PAR
Forget
LHA BSGOM
Forget meditating on Medicine Buddha.
LHA BSGOM forget doing
Medicine Buddha's mantras.
BYED RGYU MED PA BZYIN MI BYED PAR
Even if you don't do anything
SGRUP PA
Don't think about those
high, high practices.
SGRUB PA NYAMS SU BLANG BYA'I GZHI MA
By the way, this MA,
Tim, is not a negative.
It's the second half of GZHI
It's interesting.
So you have to be careful.
It means that the super foundation,
like the mother foundation.
GZHI MA
BYANG CHUB LAM RIM DANG,
DE'I NANG NAS KYANG BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS
'DI LA BYED DGOS KYI
He says, forget secret mantras.
Forget a meditation on
even Medicine Buddha.
Right now, if you focus on this feeling
that I would like to
dance between the planets
and help other beings there,
you focus on that feeling,
and that's enough for your practice.
That's extremely powerful
Vajrayana practice
is to love other people
enough that you want to dance
between a billion planets and help them.
Keep that vision in your mind,
and it's as powerful as tantra.
Keep that vision in your mind.
Then he says in the next sentence,
'DI MED PA MI TSE RI STONG DU BSKYAL TE
RI STONG
RI means a mountain.
Like when we do the mandala, we say
RI'I RGYAL PO RI RAB
which means the mountain.
Mount Мeru.
STONG means empty. So,
RI STONG means you climb up
to the Himalayan mountains,
you find a cave and you start meditating.
GZHAN JI 'DRA ZHIG BSGOM KHUL BYAS KYANG
Doesn't matter what you do.
By the way, Tim, the KHUL is new for you,
K-H-U-L
That means, act like
you're doing something.
Like you go through the motions is KHUL
It doesn't mean cool.
So when you add it to a verb,
it means, yeah yeah you
look like you're meditating.
You look like you went up on a mountain
and you're sitting in a cave,
and you look like you're meditating.
You're going through all the motions
BYAS KYANG But
SANGS RGYAS KYI GO 'PHANG
DANG CUNG ZAD KYANG
NYE RU MI 'GRO BAS
If you don't have this
bodhisattva's vision,
you can spend a whole lifetime
in a meditation cave in the Himalayas
and you will not get closer,
NYE RU
you will not get closer
to Buddhahood, at all.
CUNG ZAD
You will not get closer to Buddhahood
if you don't have this vision.
'DI NYID THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL DU GNANG DGOS
So this is an important
new word for everybody
THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL
Say: THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL
MTHIL means the palm of your hand
And it also means the sole of your foot.
This is where you get your wheels
when you get the marks
of a Buddha, for example,
on your MTHIL
But in Tibetan, spoken Tibetan,
when you say put it in
your palm of your hand,
similar to the title of this book,
it means keep that as your main practice.
There's something... You
got a picture for me?
Yes. Keep this feeling
in the palm of your hand.
It means
THUGS DAM GYI MTHIL
means keep that as your
number one practice.
THUGS DAM It means in
the palm of your hand,
in Tibetan means, keep that vision
of you dancing between planets.
Keep that as your main,
main, main practice.
That's called the practice
that's in the middle of
the palm of your hand.
It's something you carry
around all the time.
DE LTA BU'I
Let's go back to the Tibetan.
DE LTA BU'I SEMS DE BSKYED PA LA'ANG,
SEMS SBYONG GI MAN NGAG
LA LTOS DGOS TSUL SOGS
This is the most beautiful
part of this Tibetan.
I'm going to say that
about a hundred times.
If you just know the instructions,
you need the instruction manual
for how to get bodhichitta,
that's all, he says, that's all.
Look, there's one page
list, stuff you have to do.
Then you get bodhichitta.
Just look, there's a very easy list.
You just follow seven instructions
and you get there.
So let's do it together, okay?
Just seven instructions.
You don't have to meditate for 20 years.
They're just seven
steps, seven easy steps.
Just do them.
And then you get it.
MAN NGAG LA LTOS DGOS TSUL
means our Lama impressed on us.
Just do those. I'm going to
teach you some instructions
and you just follow them.
KUN SLONG 'CHOS LUGS
MDOR BSDUR SHIG STZAL NAS
Every time that you
start a dharma teaching,
you have to get your
students into the mood.
You have to say, look,
the virus was nothing.
Four million people,
three million people die, is nothing.
Seven billion people
died, that's something.
Eight billion people
So don't forget. Why are we doing Lam Rim?
The virus was nothing. Three
million people are nothing.
Seven billion people going to
die if we don't do something.
They're not going to die from the virus.
They're going to die from getting old
and die.
We already had a virus before the virus.
It was called "living."
We're all going to die from it.
So he says, don't forget the motivation,
why we are here,
why we are studying Lam Rim.
Don't forget that on the seventeenth day,
the teacher, Pabongka Rinpoche,
reminded us why we were here.
So never forget.
SNGON DU JI LTAR SONG BA'I
SA BCAD RNAMS GSUNGS RJES
That RJES means afterwards.
It means he went through the outline
that we covered in the last course,
which I just did with you,
the ten benefits of bodhichitta.
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS KYI
PHAN YON DANG BTANG SNYOMS
He reviewed the ten
benefits of this vision
of the bodhisattva,
which we just did in the last class.
BTANG SNYOMS BSGOM PA
LA BSKYAR BSHAD MDZAD
And he talked about,
you're going to build this
seven steps to bodhichitta,
you're going to build them on upeksha
what's upeksha, Timothy?
upeksha
Equanimity. Yess
So don't forget, you
got to have equanimity
before you can build love on top of it.
You have to treat people equally
before you can learn to love people.
Before you can really
learn to love people,
you have to see people as equal.
So he explained it
BSKYAR BSHAD MDZAD
means he repeated from the last class
and then we went on to the new class.
So here's the new class.
DE NAS BYANG CHUB SEMS
SBYONG GI MAN NGAG BDUN GYI
DANG PO NI MAR SHES YIN LA
You guys, should learn the word MAR SHES
MAR SHES in the second line.
First part of this second line.
MAR SHES
Yhis is what we're
going to focus on today.
It's called MAR SHES
MAR SHES means realize,
they are your mother.
This is the first step
to developing that bodhisattva's vision.
You have to understand
they are your mother,
MAR SHES YIN LA
Then he says,
'DI RGYUD LA SKYE SHIN TU DKA'
It's extremely difficult to reach.
This RGYUD means mind,
to develop this in your
mind, is extremely difficult.
To really believe that
the people around you
have been your mother
is extremely difficult.
RGYUD LA SKYE DKA' ZHING,
MA SKYES NA DRIN DRAN
SOGS RGYU 'BRAS PHYI
MA RNAMS MI 'BYUNG BAS
But if you don't get past through
this first step of the seven,
you can forget trying to be a bodhisattva.
If you don't get to the
point where you realize
that all the people around
you have been your mom before,
forget being a bodhisattva.
Not possible.
So, okay,
Pabongka Rinpoche says,
Look, I know it's difficult,
it's not easy, but we got to start there
and you got to recognize
that everyone has been your mother.
'DI LA NAN TAN 'BAD DGOS
means so you got to
work hard on this, okay?
You got to focus at the beginning
on treating, seeing
people have been your mom,
that's all.
You have to focus on
that at the beginning.
And then he says,
DE LA RGYU DANG PO MAR SHES NI,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD GNYEN GYI MTHAR THUG
GNYEN GYI MTHAR THUG
GNYEN means relation,
like relative in your family.
GNYEN GYI MTHAR THUG
means ultimate relative,
which is your mom.
MAR SHES STE, 'DI RGYUD LA MA SKYES NA
BYANG CHUB SEMS KYI SKAL BA CHAD PA YIN
If you can't recognize
that everybody around
you has been your mom,
then you don't have the SKAL BA
What's that mean, you guys?
Do you remember, Jigme?
SKAL BA
You don't have SKAL BA
CHAD means like RDO RJE GCOD PA
What's that mean?
You cut the possibility of Buddhahood.
If you can't reach the
state of mind where you see
that everyone has been your mom,
SKAL BA CHAD means
you don't have the good
karma to be a Buddha.
You will never be a Buddha.
SKAL BA CHAD
That karma seed is cut in you.
You don't have a choice.
You have to work on this idea
that everyone has been your
mom. The most important one.
I love this picture of my mom.
This is me with my mom
and... I don't know.
I'll tell you, I'm sixty eight years old.
My mom died over forty years ago.
I don't think about her
as much as I used to.
I used to think about her all the time.
I used to cry all the time.
Then slowly, as you get
older and older and older,
and you start... You don't
think about your mom as much.
But if you do think about your mom,
the point of this
meditation is: let's go back
to remembering what our mom did for us.
Let's go back to remembering
that everyone has been my mother.
He says,
GZHAN ZAB MO STONG PA NYID SOGS NI
RIGS PA'I SGO RNAM GRANGS
MANG PO NAS BSAM CHOG PAS
Look, you can meditate
on emptiness, it's okay.
You can learn all the
arguments for emptiness.
Yes, you can spend your time
RIGS PA'I SGO RNAM GRANGS MANG PO
means you can use logic
and reasonable thinking to establish
ZAB MO STONG PA NYID profound emptiness.
CHOG PA means yes, yes, you can do it.
CHOG PA means yes, you could
spend your time like that.
DE TZAM DU RTOGS PAR MI DKA' MOD
Getting to see that
everyone has been your mom
is not as hard as that.
I admit it's harder to see emptiness.
DE TZAM DU RTOGS PAR MI DKA' MOD
That's... I understand
that seeing emptiness is difficult
and yes, if you tell me,
is bodhichitta easier
or is emptiness easier?
I got to say maybe
emptiness is very hard. But,
'DI LA LUNG ZHIG GIS BSAM NA'ANG,
BSAM PA'I GTING NAS NGES SHES
RNYED PA ZHIG 'BYING DKA' LA
But I have to say
something about recognizing
that everyone around you is your mom.
It's not going to be enough
to just think about it.
You can't sit there, oh, Geshe-la said
everyone's been my mom.
So you're not going to get
to bodhichitta that way.
It's not enough. He says,
DBANG RNON CHOS KYI RJES 'BRANG
Those of you who have a high spiritual IQ,
RIGS PA
You're going to have to use,
you're going to have to think your way
through this kind of love.
You're going to have to think your way
through this kind of love,
and then you can reach it.
But you got to learn to think clearly.
Clear thinking is how you're going
to reach this kind of love.
Not by saying, oh, my
mom was so beautiful,
and I love my mom, and I
feel good about my mom,
and I wish that my mom was
still alive, that's okay.
But if you don't think
your way through it,
he says, you will never reach bodhichitta.
You have to think your
way to that kind of love.
DGOS SHING
Then he quotes
RNAM 'GREL
RNAM 'GREL is a book
by Master Dharmakirti.
It's called Pramanavarttika.
It's a commentary on accurate perception.
It is the mother Buddhist
book about clear thinking,
how to be... how to think clearly.
The next picture here,
you can see
smoke coming up out of a forest.
This picture is extremely important
for a Buddhist.
This picture, if a Buddhist
sees this picture they say,
ah, I know what you're talking about.
I know what you're talking about.
Under that smoke there's
definitely a fire.
In the forest, there's a big, red fire
behind the green trees,
but we can't see it, right?
All we can see is the smoke.
If there's smoke, there's fire.
In this case, in the Lam Rim,
the fire means everyone you ever met
in your life was your mom.
That's the fire.
What's the smoke?
We have to look for the smoke.
We have to look for the proof
that the people around
me have been my mom.
We have to try to find the proof.
The smoke is the proof
that there's a fire.
Now what's the proof that
everyone has been my mom?
You know, Geshe-la, give me the proof.
It's not enough for the
Lama to describe it to you.
And it's not enough to meditate
about how much you love your mom.
You must understand
the reason why everyone
has definitely been your mom.
There's no choice.
You got to use a special kind of thinking
to prove to yourself beyond the doubt
that everyone has been your mom.
And until you go through
that mental exercise,
it's hopeless.
You won't be able to get bodhichitta.
It's never going to happen.
So now we're going to go on
a big trip in the next class.
The next class is a long class.
So get some popcorn before
you start the next class.
And I'm not going to stop.
It might take a while.
But we're going to go.
He mentions the Dharmakirti.
And he mentions that Dharmakirti proved
that everyone has been your mom
but he doesn't give you the whole proof.
So guess where we're going to go?
We're going to go to Dharmakirti
and we're going to go
through Dharmakirti's proof.
It's tough.
And it's delicious.
So see you in the next class.
We'll prove that everyone's been your mom.
See you then.